A Guide to the Records of the Instructive Visiting Nurses Association 1902-1999
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Records of the Instructive Visiting Nurses Association 1902-1999
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
90/Feb/7
17.26 linear feet
IVNA
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Materials are on loan from the IVNA
Biographical/Historical Information
The IVNA was originally founded as the Nurses' Settlement, by nine nurses in the 1900 graduating class at Old Dominion Hospital, and Miss Sadie H. Cabaniss, Director of Nursing, Old Dominion Hospital. The Nurse' Settlement was incorporated by an act of the legislature in 1901. Shortly afterwards, the Rt. Rev. Robert A. Gibson spoke to the women of the Episcopal churches in Richmond asking them to support the Nurses' Settlement. The women formed a committee, with Mrs. Valentine as chairman, and agreed to support the Settlement. In 1902, Miss Nannie Minor, a Settlement nurse, spoke to Mrs. B. B. Valentine's Womens Club. Her speech led to the organization of the Board of Trustees for the Nurses' Settlement, later known as the Instructive Visiting Nurses Association. Miss Cabaniss became the first Chief Nurse. She remained as Chief Nurse until 1909, when she resigned to form rural nurses settlements in Hanover County. Miss Minor became Chief Nurse in 1910, remaining until 1921.
The IVNA opened the first tuberculosis clinic, in 1903 on Oregon Hill; opened tuberculosis dispensaries in 1907; established a mission kindergarten in 1910, with Miss Lucy Witt as teacher. They also loaned an IVNA nurse, Miss Roller, to be the first woman Probation Officer, in 1912; hired the first black nurse in 1913; bean industrial nursing in 1914; set up the first crippled children's clinic, with Dr. William T. Graham, in 1916; and in 1920 began the first pre-natal clinic. The crippled children's clinic became Children's Hospital. Miss Witt's work, as kindergarten teacher, led to the first social work caseload in Richmond; eventually forming the Social Workers' of the Nurses' Settlement. The two wings of the Nurses' Settlement formally separated in 1922; the Nurses' Settlement ceased to exist. The IVNA and the William Byrd Settlement House took its place.
Until the 1950s, members of the Board of Trustees were involved in the day to day work of the IVNA. They did the office work, raised money, supplied and ran the loan closet, and volunteered in clinics.
In 1953, the IVNA and the City Health Department combined for reasons of economy, efficiency, and continuity of service; with each retaining their own budget. In 1961, two positions for physical therapists were established in the budget of the IVNA. That year, a new study was made by the Richmond Area Community Council to determine areas of responsibility for the IVNA and the City Health Department. By 1964, questions arose about the viability of continuing the combined service. Finally in 1966, the IVNA became an independent volunteer agency again; partially funded by the United Givers' Fund they had joined in 1960.
Scope and Content Information
The records are generally complete from 1900 to 1990. However, there are few or no records for the years 1943 to 1950.
Series 1, History, contains two handwritten speeches by Miss Nannie Minor. One is thought to be her 1902 speech given to the Womens' Club of Richmond: the other is her 1910 report to the Board of Trustees. There are histories of the IVNA, written various persons. Also included are histories of the Social Workers', Camp Harrison, and Crippled Children's Clinic.
Series 2, the Board of Trustees, contains Board minutes for 1902-1997. Also included annual reports for 1903, 1906, 1910 - 1911, 1916 - 1982. Annual reports for the years 1907, 1909 - 1923, 1928 - 1942 may be found within the minutes for those years. This series includes correspondence; financial audits for the years 1924-1945, 1947-1948, 1951, 1954-1964, 1966-1972; and miscellaneous committee reports. The monthly minutes kept by the Board of Trustees contain information about the role of women in Richmond's community life. The reports by the Director or Chief Nurse, to the Board of Trustees, includes information about the range of problems nurses faced, particularly during the early twentieth century.
Series 3, Legal, contains correspondence, legal records, contracts, wills, constitutions and by-laws and legal complaints against the IVNA. Most of the correspondence is with the IVNA's long time legal representative Thomas Gay.
Series 4, Organization and Staff of the IVNA, contain a staff manual, date unknown, and information about the work performed by the director and nurses, mainly from the 1950s to 1982. However early information may also be found in the minutes of the Board of Trustees. Information about the IVNA - City Health Department combined services and separation is included. Also included is information about the South Richmond Community Nursing Service, a precursor to the combined services. This series contains the papers and studies done by the staff, particularly Marie Lowe, Director of the IVNA from 1957 to 1963, and Ruth Freeman, of Johns Hopkins University. Oversized estimated budget records have been separated; they are located in Box 42.
Series 5, Photographs, consists of photographs and snapshots of organizational activities and its members. Some of the photographs have been identified; most date from the 1950s and 1960s. The photographs are mostly black and white and range in size from 2"x 3" to 9" x 12". Series 5 has not been arranged.
Series 6, Miscellany, contains scrapbooks, morbidity statistics, and newspaper clippings. The scrapbooks are dated in the late 1920s, the 1940s, the 1950s, the 1960s, and the 1970s. Their contents include miscellaneous correspondence, photographs, snapshots, newspaper clippings, and other memorabilia. Two morbidity volumes contain statistics; one volume, dated 1946 - 1953, has statistics about various conditions as well as maternity statistics. The second volume, dated 1946 - 1952, contains statistics for discharged cases. Dates for the newspaper clippings are unknown.
Arrangement
Series 1, History, is arranged categorically. Series 2, Board of Trustees, Series 3, Legal, and Series 4, Organization and Staff, are arranged by subject, then chronologically. Series 5, Photographs, and Series 6, Miscellany, are not arranged.
Contents List
- Series 1: History
  - Documents 1900-1903 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Speeches by Nannie Minor 1902, 1910 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Copies, Nannie Minor's speeches (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Fragment, Sadie Heath Cabaniss (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Minute Book, Episcopal Church Committee 1902-1909 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - History 1900-1940 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - History 1940-1949 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - History 1949-1976 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Newspaper Articles, History (Box-folder 1.9)
  - History, through 1939 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - History, Master's Thesis 1900-1950 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Camp Harrison (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Social Workers (Box-folder 1.13)
  - IVNA Social Work Separation (Box-folder 1.14)
  - The Nurses Settlement of Richmond (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Nurses Settlement of Richmond (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Standards in Visiting Nurse Work (Box-folder 1.17)
  - History of the Crippled Childrens Hospital (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Brochures-IVNA (Box-folder 2.2)
  - IVNA History (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Published Articles on IVNA (Box-folder 2.4)
  - IVNA Flyer (Box-folder 2.5)
  - History 1940-1945 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - IVNA-Source of Income (Box-folder 2.7)
  - Histories (Box-folder 2.8)
- Series 2: Board of Trustees
  - Subseries A: Minutes
    - IVNA Minutes 1902-1909 (Box-folder 3.1)
    - IVNA Minutes 1907, 1909-1915 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - IVNA Minutes 1916-1923 (Box-folder 3.3)
    - IVNA Nursing Committee Minutes (Box-folder 3.4)
    - IVNA Monthly Minutes 1924-1928 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - IVNA MInutes 1926-1936 (Box-folder 3.6)
    - IVNA Minutes 1928-1929 (Box-folder 3.7)
    - Minutes 1930-1931 (Box-folder 4.1)
    - Agenda, Board Meetings 1932-1946 (Box-folder 4.2)
    - Minutes 1932-1933 (Box-folder 4.3)
    - Minutes 1934-1935 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - Minutes 1936-1937 (Box-folder 4.5)
    - Minutes 1938-1939 (Box-folder 4.7)
    - Minutes 1940-1941 (Box-folder 4.7)
    - Minutes 1942 (Box-folder 4.8)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1945-1946 (Box-folder 4.9)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1947-1950 (Box-folder 4.10)
    - IVNA Minutes 1948-1966 (Box-folder 4.11)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1951-1954 (Box-folder 5.1)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1955-1958 (Box-folder 5.2)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1959-1961 (Box-folder 5.3)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1961-1962 (Box-folder 5.4)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1963-1965 (Box-folder 5.5)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1966 (Box-folder 5.6)
    - IVNA Minutes 1967-1978 (Box-folder 5.7)
    - Board of Trustees Minutes 1967-1969 (Box-folder 6.1)
    - Board of Trustees Minutes 1970-1971 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1974-1977 (Box-folder 6.3)
    - IVNA Minutes 1979-1992 (Box-folder 6.4)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1978-1981 (Box-folder 6.5)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 6.6)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1983 (Box-folder 6.7)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1984 (Box-folder 6.8)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1985 (Box-folder 7.1)
    - IVNA Board of Trustees Minutes 1986 (Box-folder 7.2)
    - IVNA Minutes 1987 (Box-folder 7.3)
    - IVNA Report Minutes 1988 (Box-folder 7.4)
    - IVNA Minutes 1988 (Box-folder 7.5)
    - IVNA Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 7.6)
    - IVNA Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 7.7)
    - IVNA Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 8.1)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 8.2)
    - IVNA Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 43.1)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 43.2)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 43.3)
    - IVNA Committee Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 43.4)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 43.5)
    - IVNA Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 43.6)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 43.7)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 43.8)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 43.9)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 43.10)
    - IVNA Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 43.11)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 43.12)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 43.13)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 43.14)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 43.15)
    - IVNA Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 43.16)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 43.17)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 43.18)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 43.19)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 43.20)
    - IVNA Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 43.21)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 43.22)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 43.23)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 43.24)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 43.25-27)
    - IVNA Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 44.1)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 44.2)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 43.3)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 44.4)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 44.5)
    - IVNA Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 44.6)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 44.7)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 44.8)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 45.1)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 45.2)
    - IVNA Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 45.3)
    - IVNA Home Health Care Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 45.4)
    - IVNA Health Services Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 45.5)
    - IVNA Committees Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 45.6)
    - IVNA Foundation Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 43.7)
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Reports 1903, 1906, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 8.3)
    - Annual Reports (Box-folder 8.4)
      1950, 1966, 1969-1972, 1975-1981
    - Annual Reports (Box-folder 8.5)
      1960, 1970-1977, 1985, 1986, 1987-1988
    - Annual Reports 1908-1912 (Box-folder 8.6)
    - Annual Reports 1912 (Box-folder 8.7)
    - Annual Reports 1912-1920 (Box-folder 8.8)
    - Annual Reports 1913-1917 (Box-folder 8.9)
    - Annual Reports 1913-1920 (Box-folder 8.10)
    - Annual Reports 1915 (Box-folder 8.11)
    - Annual Reports 1916 (Box-folder 9.1)
    - Annual Reports 1916-1919 (Box-folder 9.2)
    - Annual Reports 1917 (Box-folder 9.3)
    - Annual Reports 1918 (Box-folder 9.4)
    - Annual Reports 1919 (Box-folder 9.5)
    - Annual Reports 1919 (Box-folder 9.6)
    - Annual Reports 1920, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 9.7)
    - Annual Reports 1920 (Box-folder 9.8)
    - Annual Reports 1920 (Box-folder 9.9)
    - Annual Reports 1921 (Box-folder 9.10)
    - Annual Reports 1922 (Box-folder 9.11)
    - Annual Reports 1922 (Box-folder 9.12)
    - Annual Reports 1923 (Box-folder 9.13)
    - Annual Reports 1923 (Box-folder 9.14)
    - Annual Reports 1924 (Box-folder 9.15)
    - Annual Reports 1925 (Box-folder 9.16)
    - Annual Reports 1926 (Box-folder 9.17)
    - Annual Reports 1927 (Box-folder 9.18)
    - Annual Reports 1928 (Box-folder 9.19)
    - Annual Reports 1929 (Box-folder 10.1)
    - Annual Reports 1930 (Box-folder 10.2)
    - Annual Reports 1931 (Box-folder 10.3)
    - Annual Reports 1932 (Box-folder 10.4)
    - Annual Reports 1933 (Box-folder 1933)
    - Annual Reports 1934 (Box-folder 10.6)
    - Annual Reports 1935 (Box-folder 10.7)
    - Annual Reports 1936 (Box-folder 10.8)
    - Annual Reports 1937 (Box-folder 10.9)
    - Annual Reports 1938 (Box-folder 10.10)
    - Annual Reports 1939 (Box-folder 10.11)
    - Annual Reports 1940 (Box-folder 10.12)
    - Annual Reports 1941 (Box-folder 10.13)
    - Annual Reports 1942 (Box-folder 10.14)
    - Annual Reports 1943 (Box-folder 10.15)
    - Annual Reports 1944 (Box-folder 10.16)
    - Annual Reports 1945 (Box-folder 10.17)
    - Annual Reports 1946 (Box-folder 10.18)
    - Annual Reports 1947 (Box-folder 10.19)
    - Annual Reports 1948 (Box-folder 10.20)
    - Annual Reports 1949 (Box-folder 10.21)
    - Annual Reports 1950 (Box-folder 10.22)
    - Annual Reports 1951 (Box-folder 10.23)
    - Annual Reports 1951 (Box-folder 10.24)
    - Annual Reports 1952 (Box-folder 10.25)
    - Annual Reports 1952 (Box-folder 10.26)
    - Annual Reports 1954 (Box-folder 11.1)
    - Annual Reports 1955 (Box-folder 11.2)
    - Annual Reports 1956 (Box-folder 11.3)
    - Annual Reports 1957 (Box-folder 11.4)
    - Annual Reports, Bureau of Public Health Nursing 1958-1959, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 11.5)
    - Annual Reports 1958 (Box-folder 11.6)
    - Annual Reports 1959 (Box-folder 11.7)
    - Annual Reports 1960 (Box-folder 11.8)
    - Anniversary Committee 1960
    - Annual Reports 1961 (Box-folder 11.10)
    - 10th Year Report IVNA Richmond Dept. of Public Works 1962 (Box-folder 11.11)
    - Annual Reports 1962 (Box-folder 11.12)
    - Annual Reports 1963 (Box-folder 11.13)
    - Annual Reports 1964 (Box-folder 11.14)
    - Annual Reports 1965 (Box-folder 11.15)
    - Annual Reports 1966 (Box-folder 11.16)
    - Annual Reports 1967 (Box-folder 11.17)
    - Annual Reports 1967 (Box-folder 11.18)
    - Annual Reports 1968 (Box-folder 11.19)
    - Annual Reports 1968 (Box-folder 11.20)
    - Annual Reports 1969 (Box-folder 11.21)
    - Annual Reports 1969 (Box-folder 11.22)
    - Annual Reports 1970 (Box-folder 12.1)
    - Annual Reports 1970 (Box-folder 12.2)
    - Annual Reports 1971 (Box-folder 12.3)
    - Annual Reports 1971 (Box-folder 12.4)
    - Annual Reports 1972 (Box-folder 12.5)
    - Annual Reports 1972 (Box-folder 12.6)
    - Annual Reports 1973 (Box-folder 12.7)
    - Annual Reports 1973 (Box-folder 12.8)
    - Annual Reports 1974 (Box-folder 12.9)
    - Annual Reports 1975 (Box-folder 12.10)
    - Annual Reports 1975 (Box-folder 12.11)
    - Annual Reports 1976 (Box-folder 12.12)
    - Annual Reports 1976 (Box-folder 12.13)
    - Annual Reports 1977 (Box-folder 12.14)
    - Annual Reports 1977 (Box-folder 12.15)
    - Annual Reports 1978 (Box-folder 12.16)
    - Annual Reports 1978 (Box-folder 12.17)
    - Annual Reports 1979 (Box-folder 13.1)
    - Annual Reports 1980 (Box-folder 13.2)
    - Annual Reports 1980 (Box-folder 13.3)
    - Annual Reports 1981 (Box-folder 13.4)
    - Annual Reports 1981 (Box-folder 13.5)
    - Annual Reports 1982 (Box-folder 13.6)
    - Annual Reports 1982 (Box-folder 13.7)
    - Board Members (Box-folder 13.8)
      1949, 1951, 1952, 1955-1959,
    - Presidents 1902-1974 (Box-folder 13.8)
    - Annual Report of President, n.d. 1961-1966, 1971 (Box-folder 13.9)
    - Annual Reports-misc., (invitations, replies etc.) 1950-1973 (Box-folder 13.10)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence
    - Correspondence-Interagency Public Health Nursing Committee (Box-folder 14.1)
    - Correspondence-Requests (Box-folder 14.2)
    - First and Merchants Bank 1928-1944 (Box-folder 14.3)
    - F and M National Bank 1934-1935, 1958-1983 (Box-folder 14.4)
    - F and M National Bank 1958-1967 (Box-folder 14.5)
    - F and M National Bank 1968-1985 (Box-folder 14.6)
    - Morris Plan Bank 1930 (Box-folder 14.7)
    - Junior League 1954-1963 (Box-folder 14.8)
    - Membership 1948-1981 (Box-folder 14.9)
    - Memorial Resolutions 1921-1973 (Box-folder 14.10)
    - Manuals from Other Visiting Nurse Association (Box-folder 14.11)
    - General Correspondence 1910-1930 (Box-folder 13.12)
    - A.H. Robins 1955-1958 (Box-folder 15.1)
    - A.H. Robins 1956-1958 (Box-folder 15.2)
    - Needlework Guild 1969-1980 (Box-folder 15.3)
    - Anna Branch Binford 1924-1945 (Box-folder 15.4)
    - Maccabees 1925-1959 (Box-folder 15.5)
    - General Correspondence 1933-1940 (Box-folder 15.6)
    - General Correspondence 1954-1960 (Box-folder 15.7)
    - General Correspondence 1963, 1977 (Box-folder 15.8)
    - Donations and Memorials 1930-1957 (Box-folder 15.9)
    - Donations and Memorials 1958-1961 (Box-folder 15.10)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance 1924-1953 (Box-folder 15.11)
    - Real Estate Correspondence 1930-1932 (Box-folder 15.12)
    - Buford Scott Correspondence 1967 (Box-folder 15.13)
    - Correspondence-Ibanez (Box-folder 15.14)
    - Correspondence-Mary Nelson Myers (Box-folder 15.15)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 15.16
  - Subseries D: Financial
    - Financial Audits (Box 16)
      1924-1945, 1947-1948, 1951, 1956-1964, 1966-1972
  - Subseries E: Committee Reports, Miscellaneous
    - IVNA Advisory Committee Reports 1960-1965 (Box-folder 17.1)
    - IVNA Advisory Committee Reports 1966-1970 (Box-folder 17.2)
    - IVNA Home Health Services Advisory Committee 1979-1982 (Box-folder 17.3)
    - IVNA Professional Advisory Committee 1986-1991 (Box-folder 17.4)
    - Community Nursing Service Meetings (Reports) (Box-folder 17.5)
    - Finance Committee 1928-1947 (Box-folder 17.6)
    - Finance Committee 1948-1952 (Box-folder 18.1)
    - Finance Committee 1950-1973 (Box-folder 18.2)
    - Finance Committee 1953-1956 (Box-folder 18.3)
    - Finance Committee 1957-1959 (Box-folder 18.4)
    - Finance Committee 1960 (Box-folder 18.5)
    - Finance Committee 1961 (Box-folder 18.6)
    - Finance Committee 1962-1963 (Box-folder 18.7)
    - Finance Committee 1964 (Box-folder 19.1)
    - Finance Committee 1965 (Box-folder 19.2)
    - Finance Committee 1973-1981 (Box-folder 19.3)
    - Finance Committee 1983 (Box-folder 19.4)
    - Finance Committee 1984 (Box-folder 19.5)
    - Finance Committee 1985 (Box-folder 19.6)
    - Finance Committee 1986 (Box-folder 20.1)
    - Finance Committee 1987 (Box-folder 20.2)
    - Finance Committee 1988 (Box-folder 20.3)
    - Fundraiser 1921 (Box-folder 20.4)
    - IPHN Committee 1946-1947 (Box-folder 21.1)
    - IPHN Committee 1946-1948 (Box-folder 21.2)
    - Sub-Committee Reports I.P.H.N. Committee 1947 (Box-folder 21.3)
    - Miscellaneous Committees 1947 (Box-folder 21.4)
    - IVNA Misc. Committee Reports 1981-1983 (Box-folder 21.5)
    - IVNA Misc. Committees 1986 (Box-folder 21.6)
    - IVNA Misc. Committees 1987 (Box-folder 22.1)
    - IVNA Misc. Committees 1988 (Box-folder 22.2)
    - Nursing Committee Minutes 1948-1962 (Box-folder 22.3)
    - Patient Services Minutes 1978-1981 (Box-folder 22.4)
    - Personnel Committee Minutes 1979-1985 (Box-folder 22.5)
    - Publications Committee 1984-1985 (Box-folder 22.6)
    - IVNA Publications (Box-folder 23.1)
    - Public Relations Minutes 1958-1962 (Box-folder 23.2)
    - Publicity Human Interest Stories Used 1939 (Box-folder 23.3)
    - Sick Room Loan Closet Committee 1946-1978 (Box-folder 23.4)
    - IVNA-Sick Room Loan Closet (Box-folder 23.5)
    - Supply Chest Committee 1946-1970 (Box-folder 23.6)
- Series 3: Legal
  - Thomas B. Gay 10/30/28-12/29/41 (Box-folder 24.1)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1/18/42-6/14/51 (Box-folder 24.2)
  - Thomas B. Gay 6/19/51-2/26/60 (Box-folder 24.3)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1959-1964 (Box-folder 24.4)
  - Thomas B. Gay 4/12/60-11/13/63 (Box-folder 24.5)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1962-1966 (Box-folder 24.6)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1/16/64-9/1/64 (Box-folder 24.7)
  - Thomas B. Gay 9/1/64-5/13/66 (Box-folder 24.8)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1965-1966 (Box-folder 24.9)
  - Thomas B. Gay 4/29/66-2/6/67 (Box-folder 24.10)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1967-1968 (Box-folder 25.1)
  - Thomas B. Gay 4/18/67-10/27/72 (Box-folder 25.2)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1969-1972 (Box-folder 25.3)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1969-1979 (Box-folder 25.4)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1973-1980 (Box-folder 25.5)
  - Thomas B. Gay 2/9/73-6/14/79 (Box-folder 25.6)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1974-1975 (Box-folder 25.7)
  - Thomas B. Gay 1978 (Box-folder 25.8)
  - Thomas B. Gay 6/22/79-12/6/82 (Box-folder 25.9)
  - Bright Estate (Box-folder 26.1)
  - IVNA Health Services By-Laws 1988 (Box-folder 26.2)
  - IVNA By-Laws 1988 (Box-folder 26.3)
  - IVNA Foundation By-Laws 1988 (Box-folder 26.4)
  - IVNA Bill of Complaint (Box-folder 26.5)
  - Contract, C.H. Oliver (Box-folder 26.6)
  - Carrie S. Freydeck (Box-folder 26.7)
  - IVNA Charter 1989 (Box-folder 26.8)
  - IVNA Health Services Charter 1988 (Box-folder 26.9)
  - IVNA Charter 1988 (Box-folder 26.10)
  - Charters (Box-folder 26.11)
  - IVNA Constitution and By-Laws (Box-folder 26.12)
  - IVNA Constitution and By-Laws (Box-folder 26.13)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box-folder 26.14)
  - Contract, American Locomotive (Box-folder 26.15)
  - Contracts 1948-1976 (Box-folder 26.16)
  - Deeds (Box-folder 26.17)
  - Estate, Mary Martin (Box-folder 26.18)
  - IVNA Lawyers Title Insurance (Box-folder 26.19)
  - IVNA Advisory Committee: Lease and Agreements (Box-folder 26.20)
  - Misc. Legal File (includes agreements Corres. etc.) (Box-folder 27.1)
  - Rapheal Levy Estate (Box-folder 27.2)
  - State Corporation Commission 1957-1983 (Box-folder 27.3)
  - IVNA Tax Exempt Status 1928-1979 (Box-folder 27.4)
  - Virginia Campbell File (Box-folder 27.5)
  - Thomas B. Gay, Re: IVNA Advisory Committee (Box-folder 27.6)
- Organization and Professional Staff
  - Organization
    - Manual Organization and Administration (Box-folder 28.2)
    - Organization and Administration Manual 1940-1948 (Box-folder 28.2)
    - IVNA Board Manual (Box-folder 28.3)
    - IVNA Board Members Manual (Box-folder 28.4)
    - Personnel Policy (Box-folder 29.1)
    - Policy Planning (Box-folder 29.2)
    - Women's Benefit Association 1922, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 29.3)
    - Women's Benefit Association 1929-1930, 1935, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 29.4)
    - Women's Benefit Association 1944-1958 (Box-folder 29.5)
    - Pre-natal Clinic (Box-folder 29.6)
    - Veterans Administration 1952, 1955, 1963-1970 (Box-folder 29.7)
    - Veterans Administration 1951-1955, 1960-1967, 1970 (Box-folder 29.8)